hello everyone this is Frank defreitis
and I would like to welcome you to
another broadcast of holotalk the
internet's laser and holography
broadcast or commonly known today as a
podcast
my guests for this installment of hollow
talk is a man I greatly admire for the
type of work he does in holography and
his name is John Claire
now John has a rather unusual approach
to holography and the fact that he goes
outside of his own laser lab and down
into caves deep within the darkness and
he takes a portable system which he
developed himself down into these caves
and makes Holograms inside the caves
now this to me is absolutely fascinating
I mean how many holographers do we have
in the world quite a few not as many as
photographers but there's quite a few
holographers
John is a singular holographer in the
fact that I don't know of that many or
any that I can recall offhand that
actually has a portable system and goes
make and goes to make Holograms out in
the world
what John does
and it's a fascinating aspect of
holography holography for me and it
always has been with the work that John
has done and it was an honor to be able
to have him come and visit us last year
when we were working on the Civil War
holography project in Jacksonville
Florida and Inglewood High School and
John came from his home in Georgia to
Jacksonville Florida and spent a day
with us and this you know with the
students and he brought his first
prototype for his uh what he calls
holography camera with him and set that
up and showed us how it works and we're
just totally fascinated by it and he has
recently made some very impressive
Holograms laser transmission Holograms
inside
uh the caves now he's been doing this
for years this isn't something that's
new he's been doing this for years I
mean I think I first met John after I
came onto the internet in the mid 90s
and he was already doing this
so I left a note on one of his personal
pages that it's very similar to the
images that were sent back from the Moon
and sent back from Mars and I'm not
exaggerating when I say that and one day
there's going to be a Rover on Mars and
it's going to be able to send back
probably via Digital Data
holographic images of the Martian
surface and rocks and
to me I mean to the rest of the world
that's going to be totally fascinating
especially if those Holograms are
synthesized you know via digital
technology into actual Holograms and
possibly even reproduced on magazine
covers for everyone to see they'll be
totally fascinated saying wow this is a
rock from Mars you know and I'm seeing
this as a hologram in front of me on
this magazine cover and it's going to me
it's going to be well you know this man
has been doing this for years you know
this is nothing new I just hope the
world doesn't forget what John Claire
not only has done but what he's doing
right now at this moment in our own live
lifetimes as you're sitting here
listening to this
so without further Ado let me turn the
interview over to John Claire now this
interview was conducted
back in December right before
immediately before I took a break for
the holiday season
and basically I had to edit it which I
have done and now I had to do an
introduction which I'm now completing
with this but it's been long overdue I
know John's been waiting for it I've
been waiting for it now John is a rather
soft Spoken Man he's not as outgoing and
flamboyant as you find me when I'm out
somewhere or on the show here
so he's rather quiet in the interview so
there's I tried to you know boost his
voice as much as possible but uh he's
very humble in what he has done and he's
a wonderful guy to know so without
saying any more I will turn the
interview over to uh we'll turn you over
to the interview with John Claire and as
always thank you for listening to
holotalk here's John Claire
hello John how are you it's Frank de
Freitas
doing good tonight
terrific terrific
great yeah I know well it's good to have
you on the show and I know a lot of
listeners are going to be looking
forward to hearing all it is that you're
going to say about doing your K
photography and I was wondering if we
could start off with that telling the
listeners a little bit about what you do
with cave holography and also some of
the new discoveries you've made with
your new pieces of equipment
yeah well cableography sudden I've been
interested in for a very long time
almost as long as I've been caving which
is real long
I started caving back in the
or something and
it's I've known about holography
about cavelography and I have tried it
way back in the 70s with the
recruiter helium neon lasers and power
supplies to head back then didn't have
much success
can uh
a few years ago I
done it again with another helium neon
laser doing just a simple one beam
reflection Holograms
nicer power supplies we have nowadays
had a great success with that
I've been trying to do the two beam
transmission Holograms
because I
impressed with the image
Emmy transmission hologram
get an image that's actually bigger than
the plate
transmission hologram as you know it's
like a window that you're looking
through at a big scene behind it yeah
[Music]
the image is always nice and
Sharp
if you're using a laser yes play it back
but I hadn't had a whole lot of look at
making transmission whole cream until
just a few weeks ago
or
try to set up in the lab at home and
seem to work okay and I go to the cave
and try and for some reason I was
getting very uh
weak images what do you think the
problem was there
um
I'm trying to figure out I thought well
maybe the cave just inherently isn't
stable enough and maybe you know it's
just foolish to uh try it and uh
you know because uh you have had some
luck doing Holograms and caves right
yeah right yeah the one beam uh
reflection but I guess you can probably
do a 1 being reflection
only
minimum ability requirements
and then like I said just a few weeks
ago I finally had some good luck at it
I was using plates this time instead of
film
[Music]
so I guess over to Thanksgiving weekend
I shot a few in this uh cave in North
Georgia and came home developed them
you know some some mediocre results I
mean they were better than I did before
and then I went back again this past
weekend and did it again and uh
I guess just made longer exposures
and I'm very happy with
the results yeah I know it's the the
pictures that you had sent
from this recent outing is that correct
the recent trip to the caves that's the
texture you sent this time yeah
and um
I'm using a more compact apparatus I had
before
and the other thing I had everything on
a breadboard
[Applause]
started out using a spatial filter for
the reference beam
and
did you run into problems doing that
well
okay when you're
in your nasty environment like a cave
and all messing around with it it's just
all that much more trouble yeah some
people could lose their mind trying to
figure out a spatial filter
I had done other experiments with fiber
optics
and I found that uh is uh
green laser the DP
SS type of laser
coherent 315 is the
brand uh
because he has extremely long coherence
length
and running into a multi-mode fiber even
if the fiber does scramble it up
apparently we started out with hundreds
of feet of coherence
even as you scrambled up down to what
maybe 10 feet go here
you still get a decent coherence out of
the end of the fiber so I was just using
that to
if they're little Edmund beam splitter
bringing it up and around and
what comes out of the end is five or
just comes out as a cone yeah
diverging
it's got a little bit of its own mode
pattern in it but after you bleach the
Hologram you don't even notice it no
kidding
really that's good you know some of the
parts would be brighter than others and
all but it really doesn't show up much
at all and when you look and when you
look at that hologram it's almost like
you're back in that cave again isn't it
isn't it yeah if that's you know
particular spot
yeah that's the weird thing about using
a fiber optic
when you develop the film before you
bleach it it looks like somebody just
splattered paint on it yeah I say oh man
and after you bleach it that's amazing
yeah
all sets up the uh polarization of laser
tuna
but yet you still get bright results
right yeah
and then I've also been uh
using what's called engineered diffuser
spread my beam out and I've tried all
kinds of different lenses all little
ball lens it's all trying to spread it
out enough to light up the whole scene
and then I I try to opal diffusing glass
it makes a nice even illumination
but it's spreads out so much that
not enough reflecting back to expose a
hologram and a reasonable amount of time
it spreads out pretty quick over short
distance doesn't it yeah
so these engineering diffusers uh
there's several different companies that
make them
when I'm using this by a company called
Luminate
l-u-m-i-n-i-t I think luminate
they're called light shaping diffusers
Salomon
different diffusion patterns uh some of
them diffuse into a round shape some of
them into an elliptical shape
it's amazing how they can shape the beam
by using those sheets yeah it's
apparently a
shows you know micro photographs of the
surface and it's
a little tiny um like bumps
shape this
pumps in a certain direction
because of
the light to go whichever way they want
I guess yeah interaction of some sort
do you plan on going back into the cave
and doing a series of these Holograms
I'm not down here this weekend you know
occasionally I do have to do some things
at home and yeah probably next weekend
I'll go back down again
caving out something
to do y'all
a few days every month anyhow it would
be great if you could get an exhibit of
this stuff
I would love to see these pieces I'm
always fascinated with what it is that
you do
you know going into caves and doing cave
holography that's that's John Claire
that's that's your own field well
uh
I'm just hoping some other people might
uh you know
inspired by this and not necessarily you
know doing the cave that you know try
someplace else you know find something
else out in nature or something
Dark Night you make a hologram with some
weird rock formations or something
Oracle thing some sort
maybe just to put a tent over it I think
it dark whatever yeah
oh Harrison's another person
I know he lived in Texas and I think he
tried doing some holograms on the beach
one time shells or something yeah I
don't think it
yeah I think I think there's been a few
people that have actually gone out and
made a few outdoor Holograms but what
you do is almost like a little field
unto yourself I mean they they go out
they try their hologram they make their
hologram and then they go back to
whatever else it was they were doing and
experimenting with and moving on to
other things but you've been doing this
years that this is
almost like your own field
unfortunately got two interests that you
know just managed to come together
what would your plans for the future be
with this anything
oh
there's some better ones
um how about larger ones you foresee
yourself doing perhaps eight by tens
yeah
right now what I'm doing is I think is a
four inch by four inches just because
the plates I had the
cut them down that was just a convenient
size with the standard plates are four
by five now how did 4x4 make them more
convenient
um the apparatus I put together the
platen that I'm using to hold the film
yeah
okay uh
looked around thinking oh what can I use
the nice stable
piece of material to put the film
against
um if it cover from a electrical box
that was the shape of it four inch by
four four inches I see
black belt over it and uh
incorporated into my apparatus do you
cut glass plates down to the four by
four okay
yeah I bought some places young that
were some odd size they morning at 8 by
by test range size that's why I got a
deal on them
I think somebody ordered them and then
you know
got the special order but didn't pay for
them
and I think their oldest can be too I
think they're manufactured in 2003 and
here it is almost 2009 I'm using them
yeah that says something about the vrp
complacency you have a long shelf life
I've never had any difficulties working
with
holographic plates that were past their
expiration date there's always a way
that you can figure out the work with
them whether it's a pre-soak or whatever
it is increasing exposure to compensate
for the age
but you can get good Holograms out of
plates that are even more than 10 years
old easy
talking about the reflection of the
transmission Holograms
another
nice thing nowadays is uh
little red diodes or cheap
yeah it used to be a problem with the
transmission Holograms is how you're
going to play it back well you have to
use a laser well
nowadays you know
red laser doesn't cost any more than a
flashlight you know so you're you're
shooting them in green and now you're
going to illuminate them with red right
okay yeah I've done that myself I find
that to be pretty convenient because I
have 100 milliwatt green here and I've
I've shot some green Holograms and then
just for convenience
illuminate them even with just a laser
pointer
and it doesn't necessarily have to be
any type of a non-mode Hopping type of
diode or anything you just need the
light to illuminate the Hologram so you
can use any diode that's out there
anything about the little red diodes is
they just naturally come out spread
already and clean is going
to yeah
see any other questions about the K
photography I don't think I have any
other questions how many years have you
been doing this now
when did you what year did you shoot
your first cave hologram well
exactly sometimes in the 1990s
one beam reflections
okay
any of the light shaping diffuser is I
think the uh trick now with this
because
throwing the energy out you need to have
a certain amount come back
control of these things
you know how much of an area you're
covering yeah so start with 100
milliwatts of spread it out over
180 degrees you're not getting anything
back with this as you're shooting a beam
of only 30 degrees wide
you do have quite a bit coming back yeah
yeah the pictures that you
were very bright
now what was that a rock formation it
looks almost like as if it could be one
of those underwater photographs too
that could be an option for you get
involved with this and making it water
tight and doing something underwater
well one of the pictures I sent
[Music]
out that
thing that are right there we call it a
drape Reformation
way the
Limestone you know you know formed over
the eons
drapery
yeah I thought it was just an
interesting thing to take a picture of
but
there are much more beautiful things in
caves it's just I'm experimenting right
now and that's
going to get in well relatively easy
again I still have to repel into it but
yeah love to have one I could just park
my car walk into it oh wouldn't that be
something but then that wouldn't be
caving anymore
the other cave enthusiasts and if you
have what has their reaction been
well I just shot him uh last Sunday and
then
three people others my wife
you know how to seen him as a
of the person that owns the cave and the
two other cavers
I'm a big fan of yours I like what it is
that you do I appreciate that and uh
I find it really interesting I've always
found it interesting
the real thing well I'll tell you what
you you send the Hologram to me and I'll
make sure that when I go out on the road
I'll make sure that I take it with me
and other people see it and give you
credit that you did it all right thank
you
we'll get a lot of different people from
a lot of different parts of the United
States take a look at it all right
give me more reason to go camping next
weekend be safe though be safe
all right we'll talk to you later all
right John thank you so much all right
bye